Guide to the Elias L. Magoon Papers, 1861-1885
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Elias L. Magoon Papers
1861-1885
Magoon, Elias Lyman
0.2 cubic feet (1 box)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
This collection consists of correspondence, reports, and other materials created or collected by Elias Magoon, most of which are related to the Vassar College Art Gallery.
Biographical Note
Elias L. Magoon (1810-1886) was an American clergyman. A trustee of Vassar College from 1861 to 1886, he also served as chairman of the committee responsible for founding the College’s art gallery. In 1864, Magoon sold over 400 works of contemporary American and British art to Matthew Vassar, who insisted on the study of original works of art for the edification of the women who attended the new College. These works are now held at the Frances Lehman Loeb Art Center.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of correspondence, reports, and other materials created or collected by Elias Magoon, most of which are related to the Vassar College Art Gallery.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Vassar, Matthew, 1792-1868; Vassar College--Art Gallery
Document Types:
Correspondence; Reports
VCL Categories:
Vassar College Trustees
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, May 2021. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, October 2025.
Acquisition Information
Source unkown.
Container List
- Letters from Elias Magoon to Samuel Caldwell, 1883-1884; [2 letters] (Folder 1)
- Letter from Elias Magoon to Registrar Willard L. Dean, 1885; [1 letter] (Folder 2)
- Letters from Elias Magoon to Benson J. Lossing, 1865-1872; [3 letters] (Folder 3)
- Letters from Elias Magoon to President John Raymond, 1875-1877; [2 letters] (Folder 4)
- Letters from Elias Magoon to Matthew Vassar, 1861 Jan - 1864 Aug; [9 letters] (Folder 5)
- Letters from Elias Magoon to Matthew Vassar, 1864 Oct-Nov; [6 letters] (Folder 6)
- Letters from Elias Magoon to Martin B. Anderson, 1838-1883; [Photocopies. Originals at the University of Rochester] (Folder 7)
- Letters from Elias Magoon to others, 1860-1882; (Photocopies. Originals at the University of Rochester] (Folder 8)
- Catalogue of the Art Gallery given to Cyrus Swan, 1864 (Folder 9)
- "Report of the Committee on the Art Gallery of Vassar Female College,", 1864 (Folder 10)
- Reports of the Committee on the Art Gallery, 1864 Feb-Jun; [2 reports] (Folder 11)
- Elias Magoon autograph, undated (Folder 12)
- Receipt from Appleton and Co. to Elias Magoon, 1858 Jun 8 (Folder 13)